we stay on this topic now and as
Government rolls ahead with the nhi are
they ignoring its many red flags let's
unpack some of these we're joined by
Discovery Health's chief executive
officer Ryan notes this afternoon thank
you very much for your time this
afternoon Ryan and there are many red
flags that have been talked about
through the last few weeks as Government
rolls out to the nhi
um as someone in the health industry
what would you say some of these red
flags are when it comes to the bull as
it was passed
thanks very much for having me review
and good to chat in the first instance I
should just make clear that at Discovery
we believe in structural reform in the
Healthcare System we recognize that
there are more than 40 million people in
South Africa who don't necessarily have
the appropriate access to high quality
health care and we do recognize the
inequality that exists in the current
system so it is our view that structural
reform is required simultaneous
regulatory change in both the private
and the public sector is needed in order
to improve access and equity and in this
regard we've been quite constructive
Rafi where we've made various
suggestions about models that could be
sustainable your question about red
flags is important we're surprised that
the Parliamentary portfolio committee
approved this ball with various minor
amendments despite multi-stakeholder
submissions and extensive input into the
first version of the bull they
effectively ignored all that input and
approved an amended version that looks
very much like the first version the two
key issues in our view are that they
send a very negative message firstly to
health professionals in South Africa and
we're working hard with health
professionals to make sure they
understand that many many years will
pass before there's any impact on them
but the sentiment within health
professionals as a result of this bull
is profoundly negative and worrying and
we've seen some negative statements
emerging from multiple doctor groupings
including the South African Medical
Association the South African private
practitioners forum and others
the other real concern from our point of
view is section 33 of the ACT which sets
out that medical schemes once the nhi is
fully implemented and there's some
discussion around what that means but at
that point medical schemes in South
Africa may only allow Top-Up cover
what that effectively means is that this
ball is proposing that the nhi it
becomes the single and only funder in
South Africa for the majority of health
care for all South Africans now we've
seen that this would land up creating a
fund much larger for example than escom
probably half a trillion Rand fund and
we think having a single fund managing
all Health Care this way is perilous in
many respects in our country
that's quite concerning because the
private healthcare sector has been quite
vocal around its concerns at its
exclusion within the involvement of the
nhi so one would wonder as you give your
explanation that you just broke down
there was there enough engagement with
the private healthcare sector Medical
Aid schemes health insurance schemes
about how it could be incorporated into
what currently exists and what could be
given to all South Africans those who
can't afford some Private health care
and of course those who can't Ryan
yes there was a process of Engagement
and you know we've participated
consistently throughout that process I
presented personally together with my
colleague Dr ayanza and ayanda and
saluba to the Parliamentary portfolio
committee and we submitted a 360 plus
page submission setting out various
thoughts and contract constructive
suggestions to address the access and
inequity issues in our health care
System we believe that an nhi will work
we're in support of a National Health
Insurance Fund but just not as the
single funder not as a monopolistic
funder we believe in a multi-funded
blended model and we think that
significant Health System Improvement is
required across the board prior to the
us being enabled able to launch a
National Health Insurance Fund so you
know to answer your question directly
engagement was there to some extent
could obviously have been better but
frankly it feels like this has fallen on
deaf ears no change has been
incorporated into the ACT whatsoever so
obviously there are reports that
litigation is going to happen and there
will be Court proceedings that will take
place because of the current uh national
health insurance bill as it stands and
one wonders what would be the ideal look
of a national health insurance
in a way that would benefit all South
Africans and we're all stakeholders
government private and other
stakeholders would be involved and
benefit to all South Africans up equally
and give them the quality of Health Care
that the nhi was premised on
yes you're right litigation does seem
inevitable should the ACT eventually be
passed and we should just pause here and
recognize that there's still a long way
to go before the ACT is promulgated into
law and perhaps you want to talk about
that a bit there are still this does not
mean that the ACT is in law yet there's
a long way to go there but at the
Parliamentary portfolio committee
hearings we're multiple stakeholders
presented not only the Private health
care sector various other stakeholders
Civil Society organizations
non-governmental organizations there
were a few of them that singled out that
unless specific elements of the ACT are
amended they intend absolutely to
litigate so it seems clear that if they
proceed on the current path that they're
on there will be litigation I should
also raise the point that the
Parliamentary law advisor
specifically in a written opinion on
this act that they wrote to the
Parliamentary portfolio committee raised
constitutional concerns specific legal
concerns about the constitutionality of
the bill
the Parliamentary portfolio committee
despite questioning from the opposition
parties it chose to ignore this opinion
and in their final report quite
strangely from my perspective chose to
Annex the Parliamentary law advisor's
opinion to the report from the
Parliamentary portfolio committee along
with approved Act
and that that seems strange to me
because frankly the opinion is quite
clear around potential constitutional
risks so that's on the litigation piece
the second part of your question
revolved around what a sustainable model
is and in our work we've done extensive
Global Research we've put together
significant Actuarial research and
proposed a health policy centered
largely around this nhi policy so it is
not radically different to this nhi
that's been proposed at all the main
difference is that it's a multi-funded
model as opposed to a single funded
model and in this multi-funded model the
funding from private contributions and
public contributions within the nhi is
Blended so that there is some risk
Equalization component so that risk is
shared across these sectors
you know coming out of the covid-19
period during which public and private
collaborated so brilliantly we think we
should build on those Partnerships and
collaboration opportunities and ensure
that in the future of South Africa's
sustainable Health policy we have the
best of all worlds participating you
know rather than really going just with
a single funder and a public health
system only Ryan thank you very much for
those insights and obviously we'll
continue this discussion as the
implementation of the nhi hopefully and
it's a best form is implemented in South
Africa that is Discovery Health that CEO
Ryan joining us this afternoon I still